Today’s daf is מנחות נ"ג. Menachot Nun Gimmel.
We started at the bottom of נ"ב עמוד ב' Nun Bet Amud
Bet and we start with a new פרק perek called המנחות. Hamenachot.
The last two פרקים prakim although we had a wonderful time dealing
with טלית, Tallis, ציצית, Tzitzis, and תפילין, Tefillin, but at least the
structure, the way רבי Rebbe structured it was things that are מעכבין
זה את זה, ma'akvin zeh et zeh, prevent one another from being
יוצא. yotzei. It started with a whole discussion, or not מעכבין זה
את זה, ma'akvin zeh et zeh, of the oil and the flour,
but then the last half, that was two פרקים prakim ago beginning,
the last half of the פרק perek we just finished discussed relationships
with מנחות menachot of the מנחה mincha and of
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and the כבשי עצרת, kevesei atzeret, the
lambs of שבועות, Shavuos, which is coming up. And then the last
part here had a whole discussion about the חביתי כהן גדול, chavitei
Kohen Gadol, about the קרבן korban that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would bring every day, half in the morning, half in the afternoon,
and also discussions about which קרבנות korbanot are מעכב זה את זה,
ma'akev zeh et zeh, which is not exactly מנחה, mincha, but those
were the two מנחה-related mincha things. And now actually there’s a major
shift. Now we’re not talking about מעכבין זה את זה, ma'akvin zeh
et zeh, we actually talk similar to items of זבחים, Zevachim, after
you get through about five or six פרקים prakim you finally sort
of start about with like the beginning of the conversation. Okay, like
here’s how you bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, so now we sort
of say, okay, here is how you would go about, here are
some of the rules about how a מנחה mincha is actually made.
Now that we’ve sort of gotten through all the things that can
invalidate and all the מעכבין, ma'akvin, now in a way we almost
start from what might have been the beginning of the whole מסכת.
masechet. So let’s take a look. Okay, so with our משנה: Mishnah:
כל המנחות באות מצה. Kol Hamenachot Baot Matzah. All מנחות menachot have
to come as מצה. matzah. Okay,
the תורה Torah says that לא תאפה חמץ, lo te’afeh chametz, you
cannot make them חמץ, chametz, you have to bring them מצה, matzah,
it’s מפורש mefurash פסוקים pesukim in the תורה. Torah. חוץ מחמץ שבתודה,
chutz mechometz shebetodah,
the only exceptions are your forty loaves of a תודה, Todah, which
is ten of
which are חמץ, chametz, ושתי הלחם ushtei halechem and the two loaves
of bread which are brought with the lambs of עצרת Atzeret which
are brought on שבועות Shavuot שהן באות חמץ. shehen baot chametz. The
תורה Torah says that they come חמץ. chametz. However, the difference still
is that the תורה Torah says very clearly besides that the מנחה
mincha is מצה, matzah, it says כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא
תקטירו ממנו אשה לה', ki kol se'or vechol devash lo taktiru mimenu
isheh l'Hashem, any leaven and any honey you shall not bring as
a sacrifice to God, and therefore על המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח.
al hamizbeach lo ya'alu lereach nichoach. So therefore even when the תורה
Torah allows for there to be certain loaves of חמץ, chametz, you
never take a קומץ kometz from them and you never place it
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So in the case of the תודה Todah
you slaughter the תודה Todah and you sprinkle the blood of the
תודה. Todah. In the case of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem you
bring the two lambs and you slaughter them, you sprinkle their blood.
The loaves themselves, no קמיצה kmitzah is ever done to put them
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So that and that way also they’re not
like a standard מנחה mincha in the sense that a standard מנחה
mincha you would burn either the קומץ kometz if it was a
normal מנחה mincha or the entire thing if it was a מנחת
כהנים. minchat kohanim. So here it is postulated as it were because
even though the תורה Torah calls one of them, well at least
it calls the loaves of the תודה, Todah, calls it a מנחה,
mincha, nevertheless it’s not really a מנחה. mincha. The other exception which
interestingly isn’t noted but we definitely came up in the previous פרק
perek is the bread that comes with the נזיר’s Nazir sacrifice. There
as well some of those loaves were חמץ, chametz, but as well
the loaves were not actually put, no part of those loaves were
put on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so let’s take a look. Why?
Why wouldn’t that be noted? I don’t know. תוספות Tosafot actually discusses,
you know, it’s bothered with, I’m sorry, I think I said a
minute ago reverse, the תורה Torah calls the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
a מנחה, mincha, it does not call the loaves that come with
the תודה Todah מנחה mincha because those are just accompanying the תודה.
Todah. Although it does call the stuff that comes with the מנחת
נסכים minchat nesachim a מנחה, mincha, so the fact that it’s just
accompanying would not be a reason not to call it. So תוספות
Tosafot is a little bothered why the loaves of the לחמי תודה
lachmei todah are included if they’re not even directly called a מנחה.
mincha. I don’t have a good explanation why by the case of
the
נזיר. Nazir. I have not seen somebody that’s directly addressed that. Okay,
so those are the things that so those come חמץ, chametz, but
certainly you don’t put from them on the מזבח mizbeach and all
other מנחות menachot come מצה. matzah. רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbe Meir omer,
now here is how you make actually you make them into חמץ.
chametz. Okay we’d say, you know, we spend a whole holiday figuring
out how to prevent things from becoming חמץ, chametz, here we’re going
to discuss those loaves that actually are supposed to be חמץ chametz
how you make them חמץ. chametz. And it’s interesting that nobody says
well you just wait for it to rise, they all assume that
you have to have some sort of type of שאור se'or or
sourdough to create the fermentation. Okay, so let’s take a look. רבי
מאיר אומר השאור בודד להם מתוכן, Rebbe Meir omer hashe'or boded lahem
mitochen, you take the שאור se'or here which basically means the sourdough
from from the middle of it, meaning you have the flour, you
know flour and water that you’re using to make your עיסה, isah,
you take a piece of of that from the middle of what
you’re making and מחמצן, mechamtzan, and you let that become ferment, you
basically turn it into sourdough, and then you put it back into
the mixture. So he says you’ve got your עשרון, issaron, whatever your
unit of flour, you add water, you take a piece of the
flour out, you put it somewhere where it’s damp and I don’t
know, somebody here maybe knows how to exactly get dark and damp
or whatever you need for it to become... For it to ferment
and it becomes sourdough, cover it up, and then you put it
back in the mixture, and I don't know, so obviously if it
takes it takes a while, so therefore you're not doing this with
כלי שרת Klei Shares so it would become פסול לינה, pasul linah,
right. Okay. So that's Rabbi Meir says.
Rabbi Yehuda says אף היא אינה מן המובחר, af hi einah min
hamuvchar, that's not ideal because you're like, so we'll see why if
he feels it's not מן המובחר, min hamuvchar, but let's see what
he says.
I mean basically the simple explanation is because if you make quick
sourdough it's not good sourdough. Good sourdough is stuff that you know
has been fermenting for a while, you know, sourdough like handed down.
R' Uzi once gave the most beautiful דרשה drasha about you know
the whole idea of getting rid of your חמץ chametz on פסח
Pesach is because and getting rid of your שאור seor because sourdough
was often like handed down, you know, grandmother to daughter to granddaughter,
you know sort of like when people also make homegrown yogurt, you
know, you keep the culture and you just keep on adding to
it. So, you know, that the whole idea of getting rid of
your חמץ chametz of like getting rid of all the bad part
of your heritage, like the מצרים Mitzrayim part of your heritage, you
know, you have all this stuff that keeps on passing down, you
have to find where we say no, that actually part I want
to get rid of.
Anyway,
so he says that's not going to be, that's not good, that's
not real sourdough, it's not going to get it good חמץ. chametz.
So what do you do? It's refreshing to hear discussion of how
to make חמץ, chametz, right? So Rabbi Yehuda says, Rabbi Yehuda says
אף היא אינה מן המובחר אלא מביא את השאור, af hi einah
min hamuvchar ella meivi es haseor, you bring sourdough from your house,
that's good sourdough, ונותנו לתוך המדה, venosno lesoch hamidah, and you put
it into the measuring, you know, vessel, וממלא את המדה, umemale es
hamidah, and then you fill it up with so you take your
own good sourdough, you put it into the thing, you say so
you know you fill up the rest of the vessel with the
required amount of flour, so now you have the full quantity of
flour and then you go on. So אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said to him, אף היא היתה חסרה או יתירה, af hi haysah
chasairah o yeseirah, you're not going to get a good measure of
flour, it'll be too big or too little. Why? But Rashi says
when you add water and you make sourdough, this sourdough could either
be more dense than flour or less dense than the normal like
just flour. If it's more dense, right, and then you're going to
so you have it as a piece of the whole measure and
you're going to measure the rest up. If it were flour, if
you just computed the amount of flour in here, right, you would
have it would fill up more space, right, because it's more dense
than flour it's taking up less space. So therefore because it's filling
up that amount of flour is taking up less space, you're having
too much flour in this measure.
It's not the
volume, no it is the volume, but it's the volume of the
flour. So he says like this: you have now a dense piece
of sourdough. If it were just flour, the amount of flour that
was in it that went into making it, it would be less
dense and would fill up more volume. So you take this dense
piece of sourdough, you put it in your measuring box or whatever
it is, your measuring vessel, okay, and then you fill up the
rest with flour, you're now going to have more flour than had
it all been flour. Okay? Because the amount of flour you have
in this piece of dough is more for the space it occupies
than had it just been flour. So that's why you would have
too much flour if you use that. Or if the sourdough is
very loose, then you would have too little flour, if it was
less dense than normal flour, then it would be too little. All
of this assumes, as
the גמרא Gemara will say, the measurement is based on the amount
of flour that went into it, not what you have right in
front of you. This leads to, I should say, interesting discussions about
generally how you figure out שיעורים, shiurim, especially when people go crazy
over חמץ, chametz, right, on פסח Pesach over מצה. matzah. Is or
anybody, you know, all these people like now you can buy like
a 300-page book on the how much is a כזית kezayis of,
you know, of how much is a כזית kezayis of an apple
and how much is a כזית kezayis of a cookie and how
much is a כזית kezayis on this. Anyway, the funniest part is
when you look up how much is a כזית kezayis of an
olive. So anyway, can't get my head around how many olives you
need to make a כזית kezayis of an olive. But the question
is, if I've got let's say a nice cookie here or a
nice piece of חלה, challah, okay, it can be the volume of
a כזית kezayis the way it is now but there's a lot
of air pockets. Or do I figure out it had to be
the amount of flour, you know, of a כזית? kezayis? Or do
I figure out the way it is now but if I were
to sort of squush it and compress it and you know, so
there's a lot of this discussion. Anyway, here the גמרא Gemara says
at least towards the issue of a מנחה, mincha, it says we
assume the measure of flour is as the תורה Torah says, עשרון
סולת issaron soles is the flour that went into it, not the
current measure if you've somehow added it and made it into dough.
You want to know the flour that went into it. I will
point your attention though, before we get into the גמרא Gemara about
this, to a little תוספות Tosafos חסרה או יתירה, chasairah o yeseirah,
the third תוספות Tosafos here. And תוספות Tosafos
says מכאן פירש רב רבינו חיים, mikan peirash Rav Rabbeinu Chaim, so
Rabbeinu Chaim explains this, דכשמודדין במדה בפסח, decheshmodedin bemidah bePesach, when you
measure with a measure on פסח. Pesach. Now, what is that measuring?
או לצורך חלה, o l'tzorech challah, or for the sake of determining
if you have enough yeast bread to make חלה, challah, you know,
that's חייב בחלה, chayav be'challah, that you need a certain amount of
flour before you have an obligation to separate חלה. challah. It's not
like חלה challah for שבת, Shabbos, to separate חלה, challah, you know,
the obligation to separate חלה challah when you're making bread. אין להכביד
על הסולת. Ein le'hachbid al ha'solet. Don't, don't sort of like, you
know, compress. So here you see they were doing this stuff already
then. Compress the flour to figure out, oh, do I have enough?
Let me really compress the flour to make sure that I, you
know, that I'm getting the right measure. No, you're not supposed to
compress it. How do you know? דאם כן נמצאת יתירה כמו לעניין
המחוס, de'im ken nimtzet yeteira k'mo l'inyan ha'machus, because then it will
be you're going to get a wrong measure. Why? Because here it's
clear if you can have sourdough that is denser than flour, right?
Think about it. Sourdough has more ingredients than flour. So the only,
right, flour plus water. So the only way sourdough can be denser
is if when we're measuring the flour we let it settle naturally.
But if when we were measuring the flour we compressed it and
got out any air pockets, then it would be impossible for the
sourdough to be denser than the flour. So תוספות Tosafot says you
see when we're measuring flour we don't, we measure it like as
it naturally falls without compressing it. Now, what is he talking about?
One thing he's talking about is חלה, challah, okay, which is, which,
you know, is interesting, he assumes that חלה challah goes by the
same measurement here of the what do you call it, of the
מנחה. mincha. The other thing he says is for חמץ, chametz, for
מצה. matzah.
Or is it a כזית kezayit of מצה? matzah?
Right. Now, what's he talking about? He's talking about a כזית kezayit
of מצה, matzah, right? Did they do that even then, did they
sort of measure the whole thing? No, actually there was a practice
about that that went with the three לחם, lechem, the three מצות
matzos that you used to actually make it out of, I forget,
I have to double check, I forget the exact amount, but anyway,
actually make it out of an amount equivalent to certain קרבנות. korbanot.
Yeah, the פרט מנחות, prat menachot, right? Because, so therefore, so it
see, so it was the מנהג, minhag, I believe that's what he's
referring to, the מנהג minhag to use a measure like an עשרון
issaron or whatever to make the, through the three מצות matzos for
מצוה mitzvah out of. So that would directly parallel what they would
do by a, by a מנחה. mincha. But anyway, you already see
the issue about how do we measure things where we care about,
you know, flour and how much? Do we do it with the
flour? Do we do it with the water? Do we compress, not
compress? It becomes a big issue about how much מצה matzah you
have to eat and about making ברכה. beracha. So let's take a
look now at our גמרא. Gemara. בעי מיניה רב פרידא מרב אמי.
Ba'ei minei Rav Preda me'Rav Ami. So רב פרידא Rav Preda asks
from רב אמי. Rav Ami. מנלן דכל מנחות באות מצה? Minalan de'chol
menachot ba'ot matzah? How do I know this הלכה halacha that all
of them have to come מצה? matzah? So he said, well, that's
an easy question. דכתיב וכתיב בה, de'ketiv ve'ketiv bah,
the thing that it's written that they have to come מצה, matzah,
so it's written, some of the מנחות menachot it says explicitly that
you should make it מצה. matzah. דלא כתיב בה, De'lo ketiv bah,
and even those that it doesn't explicitly make it מצה, matzah, כתיב
בה, ketiv bah, but it does say by it, זאת תורת המנחה,
Zot torat ha'mincha, this is the law of the מנחה, mincha, this
is the beginning of צו. Tzav. הקריבו אותה בני אהרון לפני ה׳
אל פני המזבח, Hakreivu otah bnei Aharon lifnei Hashem el pnei ha'mizbe'ach,
top of נג עמוד א. nun-gimmel amud aleph. והנותרת ממנה, Ve'ha'noteret mimena,
what is left over from it, יאכלו אהרון ובניו. yochlu Aharon u'vanav.
מצות תאכל, Matzot te'achel,
it should be eaten as מצה. matzah. Now, of course, if you
can't eat it as מצה matzah if you didn't bake it as
מצה, matzah, right? You can't make חמץ chametz into מצה. matzah. So
therefore, if you have to, here it says it has to be
eaten as מצה, matzah, and this is the law of the מנחה,
mincha, presumably all מנחות, menachot, so you see, מנחות menachot have to
be מצה. matzah. Okay, so let's continue. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה, Amar leih, he says back to him,
מצוה לא קמיבעיא לי. Mitzvah lo ka'mibaya li. That it's a מצוה
mitzvah to do it, I'm not the question, yeah, I know the
פסוקים pesukim too. It says you're supposed to do it מצה. matzah.
But here was my question. כי קמיבעיא לי לעכב. Ki ka'mibaya li
l'akev. I wanted to know that how do I know if I
don't do it that way, it's not valid? Because remember, you know
the general principle by קדשים kodashim is is that you need the
תורה Torah to repeat something to tell you that if you don't
do it, it's invalid. Okay, so how do I know that? Now,
of course, here you could have said that maybe it shouldn't have
needed it to be repeated, maybe it's a little more intuitive, maybe
it defines like the object itself. You know, I mean a מנחה
mincha is the manufactured object, right? A קרבן korban comes from the
natural world of an animal. So you know, if when the תורה
Torah says that this animal has to be let's say male, an
עולה olah has to be male, you know, I don't remember the
גמרא Gemara ever saying, well, where did it repeat it so I
know a female is no good? You know, some things you sort
of take for granted that that's the object we're talking about. It's
not a ritual, it's not a detail of exactly where do you
sprinkle the blood. It's basically defining what are the valid objects. So
by analogy, you would have thought you don't need it to be
repeated by the מנחה. mincha. Since it's manufactured here, the idea of
baking it מצה matzah is not like a ritual of exactly where
do you sprinkle the blood. The baking it מצה matzah is defining
what type of an object are we talking about. You know, what
type of a and therefore if it's not that, it's not good.
But the גמרא Gemara is not going there. The גמרא Gemara assumes
like all other things it needs to repeat it, and if it's
not repeated, maybe בדיעבד be'diavad it would be good. So how do
we know that if it's not מצה matzah it is no good?
You had a question, Barry?
No, I'm just.
Okay. So let's see what...
You can make it so many ways that it wouldn't be some
type of detail like where do you sprinkle the blood.
I'm just saying because it actually defines... means not first it defines,
it actually defines
the way you know, what was, one more time what was your
question? Meaning it could be made in many ways, but the whole
point is that this is a manufactured item, and if the Torah's
telling you this is the way it's supposed to be manufactured, in
my mind it's not describing the way you bake it is not
so much a ritual of how it's brought, it's getting the right
object to be brought. So if you're describing this is the object
we mean, right? We need a מנחה mincha that looks like this,
deep pan, this way, that way, מצה, matzah, so basically to me
is more intuitive to say if that's not it, then it's not
the מנחה, mincha, not like oh, it's a technicality of a ritual
and maybe it's still good.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara thinks that it's the same question, so at
least you have the גמרא Gemara to back you. Okay, so אמר
ליה ואכב נמי כתיב, amar lei va-akiv nami ketiv, you've got a
פסוק pasuk also that tells you without doing it it's no good.
Why? It says לא תאפה חמץ. lo te'afeh chametz.
So you have two פסוקים. pesukim. One says you shall eat it
מצות, matzot, מצות תאכל, matzot te'achel, and the other says לא תאפה
חמץ. lo te'afeh chametz. So it's repeating, essentially don't make it חמץ
chametz is the same as saying make it מצה. matzah. So there
you go, so we have it covered by positive and negative, we
have it repeated. So the key set back to him, מתקיף ליה
רב חסדא, matkif leh Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda asked on this answer,
ואימא לא תאפה חמץ אלא שאור. ve-eima lo te'afeh chametz ella se'or.
Says one minute, there's not, it's not that the opposite of מצה
matzah is חמץ. chametz. Well, maybe it is the opposite, but it's
not that the world is defined by מצה matzah and חמץ. chametz.
There's a middle space, the excluded middle. Like, right? Things to be
defined as A and not A, but if you're saying in A
and B, sometimes there's a gap between A and B. So the
world could be divided between חמץ chametz and non-חמץ chametz or מצה
matzah and non-מצה. matzah. But חמץ chametz and מצה matzah leaves a
gap in the middle. What's this gap in the middle? שאור. se'or.
שאור se'or is not the same as
sourdough, שאור se'or is what the גמרא Gemara elsewhere calls חמץ נוקשה.
chametz nuksheh. It's some type of not fully fermented bread. Okay, it's
not yet חמץ, chametz, but it's no longer מצה. matzah. It's somewhere
in the middle space. And therefore he says how do I know
that if you do it in this sort of quasi-חמץ, chametz, how
do I know that it's not good? So I'm violating,
I'm violating that it should be מצה. matzah. Okay, but that it
only said once. So maybe בדיעבד bedi'avad it's good. Oh, it says
don't do it חמץ. chametz. This isn't חמץ. chametz. This
is some quasi-חמץ, chametz, not real חמץ. chametz. So therefore, how do
I know that it is not good?
Question: how does this fit in with like a whole
18 minutes thing?
Well, in the גמרא Gemara the 18 minutes are not the emphasis,
the emphasis is the physical signs that you see on the dough,
and that we'll talk about in a minute. So let's see. Yeah,
we just use the, no, no, we use it because it is
a שיעור shiur that is given and because we like to quantify
everything, which makes our life simpler, we hone in on the 18
minutes. But in the גמרא, Gemara, the greater emphasis for whether something
has become חמץ chametz or not is what type of physical characteristics
you see in the dough that you're working.
Just figuring it out, you know, it could even be before 18
minutes if it starts to,
yeah, it has those middle characteristics where it's not yet enough to
show that it's really fermenting, but it's no longer totally unfermented. And
we're about to describe it. So today it would be מצה? matzah?
If you went by the physical characteristics, then in theory, yes. What
happens when the different ways of measuring contradict is what you're asking?
Okay, so that's not clear. I mean, when we learn פסחים, Pesachim,
we can talk about it, I'm serious. But there are different measurements.
One is a clock measurement and the other is the evidence you're
looking at in front of you. Okay, so let's take a look.
So it says if there is something that is both not חמץ
chametz and not מצה, matzah, okay? This thing that has begun to
ferment, but hasn't really fully fermented, not חמץ, chametz, not מצה, matzah,
maybe I should be יוצא בדיעבד? yotzei bedi'avad? I'm not doing the
פסוק pasuk of bringing it מצה, matzah, but I'm not violating the
פסוק pasuk of don't do חמץ. chametz. So therefore, since it's only
one פסוק pasuk and not two, maybe בדיעבד bedi'avad it would be
good. That's the question. So let's discuss what is this middle phenomenon.
Okay, so אלא שאור. ella se'or. שאור דמאן? se'or de-man? Whose שאור?
se'or? Okay, אי רבי מאיר אי רבי יהודה? ei Rabbi Meir ei
Rabbi Yehuda? מצה מעליא היא? matzah me-alya hi? Now, there is a
debate in the גמרא פסחים. Gemara Pesachim. The following of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, interesting, the same people are
debating here. Here's the debate: when you start, you're making dough. Maybe
some people who make dough can tell me because I haven't made
dough in I don't know how long,
even when I made dough it was with one of those bread
machines. I don't think I've ever really made dough. Anyway, there you
are, you're making dough and you're not, as long as you're working
the dough, it doesn't ferment. That's a very important principle. But if
you leave it alone, then it can start to ferment. Okay, and
it starts to ferment, what happens? So first the crust starts to
like get hard or somehow the shape of the, you know, the
outer layer begins to crust. That's the הכסיפו פניה. hichsifu paneha. And
then at a later stage, cracks start appearing at the crust layer.
Okay, so at which stage am I concerned that this is already
this middle category שאור? se'or? Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
very strict. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the following: first he says
that when it starts to crust, that's already a problem. And he
says that at that stage, you actually will get מלקות, malkut, you
will get lashes. It won't be at the חמץ chametz you get
כרת karet for, it won't be full חמץ, chametz, but it'll be...
As you eat it on פסח.
Pesach. I'm sorry, if you eat it on פסח, Pesach, right, that's
where the debate is. The debate is about חמץ chametz on פסח.
Pesach. Okay, so if you eat it on פסח, Pesach, once it
crusts over that's already quasi חמץ, chametz, and we learn from a
פסוק pasuk כל מחמצת לא תאכלו kol machmetzes lo socheilu to include
even
this quasi חמץ, chametz, חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha and he says you'll
get lashes. If it gets beyond that, if it ever starts actually
having these like spider, you know, cracks, the גמרא Gemara describes it
now as a spider web, it describes it as the horns of
a locust. Okay, but whatever, it starts having these, you know, lines
and cracks at the surface, then he'll say that's real חמץ chametz
and then you get כרת. kares. So רב מאיר Rav Meir has
two things. First he holds that there exists this middle category called
חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha and he and that you get lashes but
it's not full חמץ, chametz, you don't get כרת, kares, and that
it starts at an early stage when the crust begins. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is lenient both ways. First of all he says it
doesn't even start at the crusting, it only starts when you see
the cracks. That's the only time I begin to be worried. And
even there I don't even really believe that it's a תורה Torah
problem yet. Even if you ate it with the crust, you wouldn't
even get lashes. It's not even yet fully fermented. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda basically might completely deny that from the תורה's Torah perspective
there is a middle category. But רב מאיר Rav Meir clearly holds
that there is a middle category and that it starts early. So
let's take a look. The גמרא's Gemara saying whose שאור se'or according
to who? Okay,
שאור דמאן, הוא שאור? se'or deman, hu se'or? אי דרבי מאיר לרבי
יהודה, ee de'Rabbi Meir le'Rabbi Yehuda, if it is רב מאיר's Rav
Meir stage of the שאור, se'or, the crusting, from the perspective of
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, what does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say about
the crusting? מצה מעליא היא. matzah malya hi. He says that's nothing,
that's total מצה, matzah, you can even eat that on פסח. Pesach.
So אי דרבי יהודה לרבי מאיר, ee de'Rabbi Yehuda le'Rabbi Meir, if
it's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda stage, which is the, you know, the
cracks according to from רב מאיר's Rav Meir perspective,
חמץ מעליא היא. chametz malya hi. So רב מאיר Rav Meir says
once the cracks start, I'm sorry, it's completely חמץ, chametz, you get
כרת. kares. So that's not an interesting category either, right, where the
interesting category is where it exists in some middle ground. So אי
דרבי מאיר חמץ מעליא היא. ee de'Rabbi Meir chametz malya hi. אי
דרבי מאיר לרבי מאיר, ee de'Rabbi Meir le'Rabbi Meir, if it's רב
מאיר Rav Meir from רב מאיר's, Rav Meir you know, stage of
concern, the crusting, from רב מאיר's Rav Meir perspective where you get
מלקות, malkus, מדלקי עליה חמץ הוא, mi de'laki alei chametz hu, if
you get lashes, obviously it's חמץ. chametz. אלא דרבי יהודה לרבי יהודה,
ella de'Rabbi Yehuda le'Rabbi Yehuda, the only question would be רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda perspective, the only issue where there's a middle ground is
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position with the cracks from רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda perspective where he says it's אסור assur and you don't get
lashes. Now the גמרא Gemara assumes, you know, you could have said
the opposite, which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to say, the
גמרא Gemara assumes that if you get lashes, it means it's real
חמץ, chametz, although as תוספות Tosfos points out, why? If it was
real חמץ chametz you'd get כרת, kares, רב מאיר Rav Meir needs
a special פסוק. pasuk. It's more likely to say that if it's
lashes but it's not כרת kares and you need a פסוק, pasuk,
it's quasi חמץ, chametz, which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to
say. And to say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you don't
get lashes, well if you don't get lashes, why is it anything?
Maybe it's only rabbinic. But at this stage that's what the גמרא's
Gemara assuming, that because he says it's אסור assur but there's no
lashes, so he's assuming it's not rabbinic and it is in this
quasi-set stage of not being חמץ chametz but also not being
מצה. matzah. That's what it assumes for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
ואסקיף לה רב נחמן בר יצחק. v'askif lah Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak.
Okay, so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asks. ואימא
לא תאכל חמץ. v'eima lo ti'acheil chametz. So that was one possibility.
Whatever it works out for רב מאיר Rav Meir and רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, one possibility is the תורה, Torah, you're telling me the
תורה Torah says twice it has to be מצה, matzah, it's not
true. Once it says it can't be חמץ, chametz, the other time
it says it has to be מצה, matzah, and there is this
middle ground, whether it's for crusting according to רב מאיר, Rav Meir,
whether it's the cracks according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, there is
a middle space where it is neither חמץ chametz nor מצה matzah
and that was not said twice that it has to be מצה,
matzah, maybe therefore בדיעבד bedieved I would be יוצא. yotzei.
Okay, so let's take a look.
We have an answer. Now we're going to have another reason why
there's a middle ground between חמץ chametz and מצה. matzah. Let's take
a look. מתקיף לה רב נחמן בר יצחק, Matkif lah Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asks, ואימא
לא תאכל חמץ אלא חלוט. v'eima lo ti'acheil chametz ella chalut. Don't
make it חמץ chametz but make it boiled, meaning what happens if
you take these, I don't know, having this is a way that
you make מצות, matzos, maybe it is, you take this dough and
before it has a chance to ferment, what do you do? You
throw it into boiling water. Okay, so there on the one hand
it's not חמץ chametz because the throwing it in boiling water stops
the fermentation process, and on the other hand it's not מצה matzah
because it did not like bake. You know, this thing is considered
to sort of freeze it in this stage and neither be חמץ
chametz nor מצה. matzah.
You actually boil the water and just before you throw it in
you turn the water down.
Okay. And that so I don't know if that would be חלוט,
chalut, maybe that would become חמץ, chametz, but if it's boiling, the
גמרא Gemara understands that that stops it from fermenting. So you have
something that is neither חמץ chametz nor מצה, matzah, because חמץ chametz
or מצה matzah is baked but baked in a way that either
has or has not fermented. This is neither.
Boiling is also a legitimate way of
cooking.
I mean I think that the גמרא Gemara I think the גמרא
Gemara just understands that the physical reality is that it doesn't. Oh
you say why doesn't it make מצה matzah if it just because
it stops the fermenting? But is it the same?
Anything different from boil?
Well
I don't know I mean it is a different process.
Thought they're different מלאכות melachos right? Different ways of baking or preparing
מצה. matzah. Just frying though. Right right.
Although the גמרא Gemara said even by the fried there was a
baking part of the frying as well right?
Oh right you can cook different from baking.
Right. Why does the גמרא Gemara assume that that boiled is not
the same is not is not מצה? matzah? Yeah
I don't know I mean it might not be bread. What?
Take baked back to bake and boil.
Yeah I don't know I mean I think the גמרא Gemara assumes
that you know that part of the definition of I mean this
is also true by the way. You're putting it in water.
Yeah part of the definition of מצה. matzah.
Well you always have water in the with the flour but here
it's cooked in water right.
It's the time. Right.
Well 18 right but but we're trying to make מצה matzah not
חמץ. chametz. 18 minutes gets it into חמץ. chametz. Here you're less
than 18 minutes. You throw it into the water right away. But
yes the גמרא Gemara does assume you know I think for example
I think you know when we're when when it's when we're learning
פסחים Pesachim or whatever you know I have like a whole תורה
Torah in the רמב"ם Rambam because the רמב"ם Rambam has a number
of things that you don't get כרת kares for. I'm trying to
remember how it exactly plays out. I have to look at the
רמב"ם Rambam again. But anyway there's a number of things you don't
get כרת kares for even though they seem to have fermented. And
it seems to me that the one of the ideas that the
רמב"ם Rambam has is that even חמץ chametz not only מצה matzah
which you're for the מצוה mitzvah is not just the physical reality
of fermentation. To describe something as חמץ chametz or מצה matzah it
has to also be described as לחם lechem as bread. So if
something is you know not bread even if it has fermented maybe
you'll get מלקות malkos maybe that's like this שאור se'or but it's
not the תורה's Torah definition of חמץ chametz or מצה. matzah. So
I think that part of it. I think that you know yes
you can cook it and if all מצה matzah means is flour
and water that hasn't fermented then you've got מצה. matzah. But if
מצה matzah means a type of an unfermented bread then you know
this is not unfermented bread. This is flour or whatever.
כהא דאמר ר' יצחק לחם
המנחה.
Ke-ha de-amar Rabbi Yitzchak
lechem ha-mincha. Right not standard מנחה mincha which shown up to be.
Does
he use the word לחם lechem by normal by a normal מנחה
mincha where it says מצה? matzah? It does not? What? No. That's
interesting. That's interesting. So that's a question whether the word מצה. matzah.
I assume your question is coming from the perspective that why don't
we just say anything that's flour and water that's unfermented is מצה?
matzah? And my answer is that I have a sense that the
חכמים Chachamim understood that מצה matzah was unfermented bread not unnot not
unfermented flour. And therefore this which is thrown boiling hot isn't was
something you wouldn't call bread. Right. Okay. So yeah.
I would just add to that something that is processed and cooked
or prepared with heat.
Right. Yeah.
Right. Right. Okay.
No because because according to wasn't there one opinion in פסחים Pesachim
that says even if you like pancakes are not like חמץ chametz
they're over on פסח? Pesach?
Well that's what I was saying that even
for even for חמץ chametz to be over on it at least
to get כרת kares you also might need the concept of bread.
Okay. Alright. So so but that seems to be the idea here
that you need a concept of bread. So he says look this
is neither חמץ chametz nor מצה. matzah. So maybe if I bring
this as a מנחה mincha בדיעבד bedieved it will be good? Yes
it's not מצה matzah but it's also not חמץ. chametz. So אימא
חלוט. eima chalut. חלוט מאי ניהו? chalut mai nihu? רביכה. revucha. So
he says one minute now this is sort of what you know
Dove is saying. It doesn't always say you know some of these
things is exactly made this way. Isn't that exactly how you make
a how you make a מנחה mincha that's רביכה revucha which is
sort of like you know boiled you know you put it in
in boiling oil? So that's essentially that exists as a type of
a מנחה. mincha. So let's take a look. אי דאיכא רביכה כתיב
בה רביכה. ei de-ika revucha ketiv ba revucha. If you're actually bringing
the מנחה mincha that's supposed to be רביכה revucha like boiled in
in oil so you're doing the right thing. That's not even a
question. והא לא כתיב בה רביכה. ve-ha lo ketiv ba revucha. And
but so how can you tell me that it should be a
הוה אמינא hava amina that it should be good if you boiled
it in water but that would have been described as a מנחה
רביכה mincha revucha and this is not a מנחה רביכה. mincha revucha.
So just saying so here the גמרא Gemara is getting to what
I sort of said I would have initially thought. Who needed to
be repeated? If you make it in a physical way that's different
it's a different type of an object. So if it's called a
מנחה רביכה mincha revucha fine throw the flour into water throw the
you know the not the what's it called the flour into not
the flour dough. Sorry throw the dough into the water. But if
that's called רביכה revucha but if it doesn't say that if it's
describing a different type of a מנחה mincha then you're bringing a
different object a non-רביכה revucha object. So let's just say it's invalid
because it's a different type of an object. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute ואימא דכתיב בה רביכה מצוה ברביכה. ve-eima de-ketiv ba
revucha mitzvah be-revucha. I can still say that if it doesn't repeat
it you have an
option and say that where it says רביכה revucha then you have
to do it that way. דלא כתיב בה רביכה. de-lo ketiv ba
revucha. If it doesn't say רביכה revucha and it calls it a
different type of a מנחה mincha so אי בעי. ei ba'ei. רבוכה
ליתי, revucha leisei, maybe you have an option. You can bring it
as a רבוכה, revucha, אי בעא מצה ליתי, i'baei matzah leisei, or
you can bring it as מצה. matzah. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying, okay, but maybe מצה matzah is not מעכב, me-akeiv, right? It
only says מצה matzah once, so this is not מצה, matzah, it's
not a problem as long as it's not חמץ. chametz. And the
Torah says it's supposed to be a different type of a מנחה,
mincha, it's a מחבת machavat or whatever, it's not רבוכה. revucha. Okay,
but maybe they're also בדיעבד b'diaved I can bring a different type
even if it's supposed to be one type, maybe I have that
option. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רבינא. matskif la ravina.
Okay, so now we basically have two possibilities. Don't tell me the
Torah says it has to be מצה matzah because it says don't
bring חמץ, chametz, bring מצה. matzah. Because first of all there is
a space between חמץ chametz and מצה. matzah. There's חמץ נוקשה, chametz
nuksha, there is boiled and maybe those could be בדיעבד b'diaved be
good, and you can't prove to me that they're no good because
it says
once it says bring מצה, matzah, the other time don't bring חמץ.
chametz. Now we're gonna have a third possibility why you can't tell
me oh the Torah says it's forbidden. מתקיף לה רבינא. matskif la
ravina. רבינא Ravina says ואימא לא תאפה חמץ, v'eima lo te'afeh chametz,
do not bake it חמץ, chametz, למיקם גברא בלאו בעלמא, lameikam gavra
belav b'alma, then you the person would have transgressed. Because it's actually
quite fascinating, you know, most of the rituals of the בית המקדש,
beis hamikdash, the details are not saying you will transgress if you
do it wrong. It just describes, here's how you do a מנחה,
mincha, here's how you do a חטאת, chatas, you שחט shecht it
here, you sprinkle the blood there, it describes the process. Here it
says it is forbidden, you may not bake it חמץ. chametz. So
you know some understand, the רמב"ם Rambam understands that the reason the
Torah is so much makes a point of not bringing חמץ chametz
on the מזבח mizbeiach and emphasizes you must bake it מצה, matzah,
you may not eat חמץ, chametz, is because you know maybe this
was part of some pagan associations that they would bring these types
of, this would be you know or actually stuff to the spring,
you know maybe this was the whole sense of fermenting and you
know fecundity and all of these, you know, all of these rituals.
What was it, what what they called, what was those things that
they would do for during the springtime, some rituals,
not fecundity rituals, but there's a word I'm looking for, fertility rituals,
fertility rituals. So therefore the Torah is saying no no no none
of that can go on the מזבח. mizbeiach. You do bring ביכורים.
bikkurim. Interesting, the Torah contrasts, don't bring it on the מזבח, mizbeiach,
you'll bring ביכורים, bikkurim, but it doesn't go on the מזבח. mizbeiach.
You bring a שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, which is שבועות shavuos which
is coming up, which is bread and which is spring and which
is you know all of that stuff, but it doesn't go on
the מזבח. mizbeiach. So anyway here the Torah emphasizes you may not.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying ironically, but maybe therefore it's not
invalid if you did. Maybe that means you the person transgressed. These
are one of a few details where the Torah is telling you
how you have to, you know, as a negative and positive prohibition
that you must do it this way, you may not do it
that way. So the גמרא Gemara ironically says okay so you as
a person have transgressed but maybe the קרבן korban remains כשר. kasher.
Okay so don't tell me the person says you're not allowed. In
the middle of days. No, no, no, real חמץ. chametz.
I mean what was the argument why real חמץ chametz I know
is invalid of these two?
The real argument I know that real חמץ chametz is invalid is
that the Torah repeated it. Once it says bring מצה, matzah, the
other time it says don't bring חמץ. chametz. So saying maybe it
repeated it to tell you that you would transgress but not repeating
it to say the importance of that core ritual, the importance of
that for you the person not to do it. Okay so if
you do it you will transgress but the actual קרבן korban will
remain כשר. kasher.
ואם לא יעלה לריח ניחוח. ve-im lo ya'aleh l'reiach nichoach. מחשבה אונאה?
mach'shavah ona'ah?
That'd be a question. Take a look. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says ואימא לא תאפה חמץ, v'eima lo te'afeh chametz, למיקם גברא בלאו
בעלמא, lameikam gavra belav b'alma, you the person will transgress, ופסולי
לא מיפסל, ve-isulei lo mirpsal,
it will not actually invalidate the קרבן. korban. So you cannot tell
me that since the Torah says don't make it חמץ chametz that
that's the way of repeating מצה. matzah. A, חמץ chametz is not
the opposite, A, there are things that are not חמץ chametz and
are also not מצה. matzah. And B, maybe it's emphasizing your prohibition
but not how it invalidates the קרבן. korban. So אף, af, how
do you know that it has to be מצה matzah even בדיעבד?
b'diaved? אלא מנלן? ella minalan? Where do we know it from? כדתניא,
k'detanya, like we taught in the ברייתא. braita. מצה. matzah. So it
says מצה תהיה. matzah tihiyeh.
This is actually what it says for one of the מנחות, minchos,
I forget which one, the מחבת machavat I think. It must be
מצה, matzah, it shall be מצה. matzah. So the ברייתא braita says
מצה. matzah. יכול מצוה? yachol mitzvah? Maybe it's only a מצוה? mitzvah?
תלמוד לומר תהיה. talmud lomar tihiyeh. It shall be. הכתוב
קבעה
חובה. hakasuv kava'ah hovah. The Torah makes it an absolute obligation. Now
of course the problem is that was by one particular מנחה. mincha.
How do we generalize that to all מנחות? minchos? So תוספות tosfos
says well maybe you know it was redundant, I could have known
it for that מנחה mincha anyway. So the fact that the Torah
went out of its way to repeat it must be מצה matzah
for one מנחה mincha is to tell you a general rule that
all מנחות minchos must be that way. So it's so anti-climactic, right?
You had all of these good ideas, you have all these פסוקים.
pesukim. I tell you you have all these פסוקים, pesukim, this middle
space, it's not חמץ chametz but it's not מצה. matzah. Maybe it's
your problem but it doesn't make the קרבן korban invalid. And then
in the end the answer you work because in one קרבן, korban,
one of the מנחות minchos it says it must be מצה matzah
and implicitly we somehow generalize. We don't we don't even know, we
don't even know how do you know to apply that to the
other cases?
I think in the, I think in ויקרא Vayikra
it says, I'll tell you which קרבן korban it is.
There, there, there,
where are we? No, I'm way too far.
Excuse me. Here.
ומנחה על המחבת קרבנך סולת בשמן תעשה, U'mincha al hamachavas korbanecha soles
bashemen te'aseh,
ויקרא ב'. Vayikra Beis.
No,
wait, maybe that's not it, one minute. Oh,
by מנחה על המחבת, mincha al hamachavas,
ויקרא ב' ה', Vayikra Beis Hey, ומנחה על המחבת קרבנך סולת בלולה
בשמן מצה תהיה. U'mincha al hamachavas korbanecha soles belula bashemen matza tihyeh.
So that is a specific מנחה מחבת. mincha machavas. How do you
know to generalize it? That, so that the basic question, how do
you know it applies by all מנחות, minchas, that the גמרא's Gemara's
not even bothering going into because it has to speculate on how
that on how that will be. Okay, so there so okay. Yeah,
but here, that's the פסוק pasuk of וכל שאור וכל דבש לא
תקטירו. vechol seor vechol devash lo saktiru. But if you look at,
yeah, exactly, but that's talking about ביכורים. Bikkurim. קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם
לה' ואל המזבח לא יעלו.
Korban
reishis
takrivu osam l'Hashem v'el hamizbeiach lo ya'alu. So it's ביכורים, Bikkurim, not
חמץ. chametz. Okay,
so interesting, although you have all of these פסוקים, pesukim, the גמרא
Gemara is saying in the end we just get it out of
a little extra word by the מנחה על המחבת. mincha al hamachavas.
Now we go on. בעי מיניה רב פרידא מרב אמי. Ba'ei minei
Rav Preida me'Rav Ami. So רב פרידא Rav Preida asked from רב
אמי. Rav Ami. מניין לכל המנחות שנילושות בפושרים ומשמרן שלא יחמיצו. Minayin
l'chol hamenachos sheniloshos befoshrim u'mishamran shelo yachmitzu. So there's a later משנה
mishna that says when you make a מנחה mincha you use lukewarm
water because if the water is a different temperature, I think hot,
then it speeds up the fermentation process. So you use lukewarm water
and you have to, you know, be very, very vigilant that it
doesn't become חמץ chametz as you're doing it, you're taking a lot
of care to constantly be working the dough and making sure it's
not becoming חמץ. chametz. So where do you get this idea that
there's an obligation to be vigilant? It's not just, you know, it's
a positive obligation, it's not just that there's a prohibition to make
it חמץ, chametz, but there's a מצוה mitzvah to be vigilant. Where
do you get that from? נלמדנה מפסח. Nilmadenah mi'Pesach. מה בפסח, Mah
b'Pesach, דכתיב ושמרתם את המצות, dechsiv u'shmartem es hamatzos, you shall observe
the מצות. matzos.
So maybe we should learn it out from פסח Pesach and here
too you observe it meaning watch it to be careful and vigilant
it doesn't become חמץ. chametz. אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, you don't
need to learn it from פסח. Pesach. בגופיה כתיב. Begufiah ksiv. In
the מנחה mincha itself it says
מצה תהיה, matza tihyeh, it shall be מצה. matza. This is the
same פסוק pasuk we quoted before. So we're making a little play
on a ה' hei and ח', ches, החייה, hachayei, sort of give
it life. So somehow, I don't even get even with reading the
ה' hei as a ח' ches how it means it, but somehow
we're reading that sort of you shall ensure that it's מצה matza
means that you shall be on top of it and vigilant and
make sure that it's מצה matza not חמץ. chametz. Okay, so anyway
that's where we learn it, but there's a positive מצוה. mitzvah. Don't
just prevent it from being חמץ, chametz, you know, be very vigilant
and in that way it's very similar to פסח, Pesach, you know,
that whole idea of vigilance right is the very central idea to
פסח. Pesach. So here it's not just saying the product is a
problem that's wrong, but there's a sense of vigilance in the preparation.
Yes.
So, you know, I don't know if you remember but at the
beginning of the מסכת, maseches, remember I was asking about like, you
know, what about they're asking about שאר משקין shear mashkin except for
water.
And we're about to show how there's an assumption right that you're
right, meaning, and there's later, right, if we get to it today
which we won't but tomorrow, you know, we'll see when it talks
about the making there's an assumption of water which never gets discussed
and is never mentioned in the תורה. Torah. So we'll discuss that
tomorrow. Okay, we're not going to. I never asked how much water.
Actually we're going to see that you're there's you have a certain
amount of latitude in terms of how much water because the גמרא's
Gemara's going to discuss about the consistency of what you're making and
it's not clear how much water you're using. So that is quite
fascinating, we'll talk about that tomorrow. Okay, so let's go on. Okay.
It's interesting the play with the ה' hei and the ח' ches
that's actually going to come up later today. So let's take a
look. והא דאפקתיה לעכב, V'ha de'afakteiah l'akeiv,
one minute, we learned תהיה tihyeh to tell me that if you
don't make it מצה matza it's invalid. No, אם כן לכתוב קרא
מצה היא, Im kein lichtov kra matza hi,
it is מצה. matza. היא hi would have been enough to say
that if you don't make it מצה matza it's invalid. מאי תהיה,
Mai tihyeh, why does it use that? שמע מינה תרתי, Shema mina
tarti, to say both. א', aleph, if you don't make it מצה
matza it's invalid. And ב', beis, the sense of תחייה techayah somehow,
you know, give it life, bring it to life as מצה, matza,
be vigilant over it that it does not become חמץ. chametz. Okay.
אמרו ליה רבנן לרב פרידא. Amru lei rabanan l'Rav Preida. So the
רבנן, rabanan, always the רבנן rabanan here רבנן rabanan means the rabbinic
students. Okay, they said to רב פרידא, Rav Preida, so there they
were in the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, רב פרידא Rav Preida was
giving שיעור shiur and they said to רב פרידא Rav Preida the
following. רבי עזרא בר
בריה דרבי אבטולס, Rabbi Ezra bar beray d'Rabbi Avtulas, Rabbi Ezra the
grandson of Rabbi Avtulas, who was presumably an important person, דהוא עשירי
לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, de'hu asiri l'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, he's tenth
generation descendant of Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, obviously a very great תנא.
tanna. And not only that, דהוא, de'hu, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah is
עשירי לעזרא, asiri l'Ezra, is
tenth generation descendant of עזרא הסופר. Ezra Hasofer. So we got a
very important person who's come here, right, he's ten generations descendant of.
Azarya and twenty generations descended from עזרא הסופר, Ezra haSofer, קאי אבבא,
kai abava, he's outside, he's at the door, he'd like to come
in and join the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So אמר, amar, so
רב פרידא Rav Pereda said, מאי כולי האי? mai kulei hai? What
is all this talking about who he is related to? אי בר
אוריין איהו, ei bar oryan ihu, if he is a בן תורה,
ben torah, אורייתא orayta is תורה, Torah, if he's a בן תורה,
ben torah, if he's, you know, fit, not תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
לא תלמיד חכם lo talmid chacham like a sage, here we're talking
about as a student, you know, he's enough, he's fit to be
part of the ישיבה yeshiva to come and learn with us, if
he's a בן תורה, ben torah, יאי, ya'ei, that's nice. אי בר
אוריין ובר אבהן, ei bar oryan u'var avohan, and if he's not
only a בן תורה ben torah but also has good יחוס, yichus,
יאי, ya'ei, that's also beautiful. Somewhat has a יחוס, yichus, יאי ויאי,
ya'ei v'ya'ei, it's doubly nice. He's also a בן תורה ben torah
and he's got good יחוס. yichus. But just יחוס? yichus? So he
says, ואי בר אבהן ולא בר אוריין, v'ei bar avohan v'lo bar
oryan, but if he's just a somebody who has parents, but he
doesn't—he's not a בן תורה, ben torah, אשא תכליה, esh techeilneih, so
let's fire consume him. Who cares? I'm not impressed with יחוס yichus
by itself, right? This is a ישיבה. yeshiva. Tell me about that
you're a בן תורה, ben torah, that's what impresses me. אמר ליה,
amar lei, so they said to him, no,
בר
אוריין הוא,
bar
oryan
hu, he is a בן תורה.
ben torah. Ah, so okay. So אמר להו, amar lehu, ליעול, leiyel,
let him come in, וליתי וליתי, v'leisei v'leisei,
and let him, you know, let him come up and come in.
Okay, so fine, welcome him into the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash.
So חזייא דהוה עכירא דעתיה, chazyei d'hava achira daiteih, so רב פרידא
Rav Pereda saw that this רב עזריה Rav Azarya was like in
a foul mood or like in a depressed mood, in a black
mood, I mean, would be the best way of translating it. Why?
So maybe the גמרא gemara doesn't say, maybe דסתם de-stam he was
in a bad mood, but maybe because, you know, presumably he was
proud of his יחוס yichus and he just got it thrown in
his face. Okay, I don't care about your יחוס. yichus. So רב
פרידא Rav Pereda saw that he was in a bad mood, so
פתח ואמר, patach v'amar, he decided, well, let's start with a little
אגדתא aggadeta to cheer him up. Okay, so here's the אגדתא aggadeta
he started with. אמרת לה׳ אדני אתה. amarta l'Hashem Adonai atah. You
said to God, God you are my God, you are my master.
It might be—how do you pronounce that? Is it
אדני Adonai or—or is it שם ה׳? Shem Hashem? Is it? Might
be שם ה׳. Shem Hashem.
Let me take a look.
What? I think it is.
You think it is שם ה׳?
Shem Hashem? Near enough anyway. What?
Okay, we'll figure it out.
One second.
אמרת ל—yeah, yeah, it's—so yeah, it's שם ה׳. אדון Adon and then
ני. nai. Okay. You said to God, you are—you are God, okay.
טובתי בל עליך. tovasi bal alecha. My gratitude or my goodness is
not upon you, which is very strange. So let's take a look
at how the גמרא gemara explains that פסוק. pasuk. So אמרה—or amra
how he רב פרידא Rav Pereda did. אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא. amra Knesses Yisrael l'Kadosh Baruch Hu. So the Congregation of
Israel said to God,
says to God, הקדוש ברוך הוא, ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu,
רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, master of the universe, החזק לי
טובה, hachzeik li tova, you know, give me some credit. Why? דהודעתיך
בעולם, de-hodiaticha ba-olam,
I've known your—I've made your fame known in the world, I've spread,
you know, to the whole world the idea of you as God.
So that's saying אדני אתה, Adonai atah, you are God, I have,
you know, I have made that known, so I should get some
credit for that.
So אמר לה, amar lah, so now the end of the פסוק
pasuk is God talking back. So
אמר לה, amar lah, טובתי בל עליך, tovasi bal alecha, no, my
gratitude is not for you. אין אני מחזיק טובה, ein ani machzik
tova, I don't have any gratitude to you. My gratitude is אלא
לאברהם יצחק ויעקב ela l'Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov for אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham
Yitzchak v'Yaakov, שהודיעוני תחילה בעולם, she-hodia'uni techilla ba-olam, that they first were
the ones that made me—my fame known in the world. שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
לקדושים אשר בארץ המה, likdoshim asher ba-aretz heimah, the next פסוק pasuk
is: To the holy ones that are in the land, ואדירי כל
חפצי בם, v'adirei kol cheftzi bam, and the powerful ones or the
mighty ones, all of my desire is in them. So meaning and
the אדירים adirim are often associated with אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak
v'Yaakov. So those are the ones that I'm going to be grateful
for. Now, what did this have to do with anything about—about, you
know, was it just סתם stam an אגדתא? aggadeta? So somebody, I
forget who, I was checking it last night, tried to say, "Well,
what he was saying to this—רב עזריה—it's Rav Azarya
your grandparents, so it's—it's not you."
No, I don't think so. That's obviously—there's an issue about grandparents and
you, but the question is: What is he saying? So one of
the מפרשים mefarshim tried to say that he was saying to him,
"You know, you should be grateful to your fellow students here, they—they
spread your fame, they told me that you were a בן תורה
ben torah and that's why we let you in." I don't think
that's what's going on. I think there's a different point about the
children and the ancestors. I think what he's actually doing is making
his—רב פרידא Rav Pereda is not so much cheering him up, he's
sort of trying to make him understand why רב פרידא Rav Pereda
is saying, "Why I'm not impressed. Don't take it personally." Right, don't
take it personally, I'm not impressed with יחוס. yichus. You know, כנסת
ישראל Knesses Yisrael says, "Look at all that we've accomplished," and God
says, "It's not—you didn't accomplish it, it's what your—it's what your ancestors
did. You know, so I'll be grateful to your ancestors. You don't
get credit for what your ancestors have done." Okay, of course that
maybe wouldn't exactly have cheered him up, you know, people are not
very ready to shift gears, especially if they have such nice יחוס.
yichus. So let's see what happens. Okay.
The idea
is
this—this person is thinking about
his
mi...
Right, right. Okay, but it seems to be that's the point. It's
about what you accomplish. So let's see how this goes out. Okay,
כיון דשמע keivan deshama so now this Rav Ezra heard דקאמר אדיר
deka'amar adir so he had this nice dresha with this word אדיר,
adir, the mighty one, so פתח ואמר patach ve'amar so he he
remembered a dresha that he had about this whole idea of אדיר.
adir. What was his dresha? יבא אדיר ויפרע לאדירים מאדירים באדירים. yavo
adir veyipara le'adirim me'adirim be'adirim. Let the אדיר adir come and compensate
the אדירים adirim from the אדירים adirim in the אדירים. adirim. What
does that mean? And there's going to be a number of דרשות
drashot like this about similar people and things or players that all
have a same type of of a of a phrase to describe
them. Yeah, that is the other question. There was no transition at
all how we got into this, so we could talk about that
too. Anyway, יבא אדיר yavo adir let the mighty one come, זה
הקדוש ברוך הוא, ze Hakadosh Baruch Hu, that's God, אדיר במרום השם
adir bamarom Hashem God is mighty in the heavens or whatever up
above, ויפרע לאדירים veyipara le'adirim and compensate or pay back the אדירים
adirim אלו ישראל. elu Yisrael. The positive? Yeah, the positive, I know,
that's why I said compensate. This is Israel שנאמר ואדירי כל חפצי
בם. shenemar ve'adirei kol cheftzi bam. That's a that's the פסוק pasuk
he's saying is not about אברהם יצחק Avraham Yitzchak it's about Israel.
Notice implicitly already he's reading the פסוק pasuk different than רב פרידא.
Rav Preida. He's not saying it's about the ancestors, it's about Israel
considered אדירים. adirim. Okay,
מאדירים me'adirim from the mighty ones, אלו המצרים elu HaMitzrim these are
the Egyptians דכתיב צללו כעופרת במים אדירים. dechitiv tzalelu ka'oferet bemayim adirim.
So the
the mighty one, not that the מים mayim are אדירים adirim here,
it's reading that the mighty ones are the Egyptians, they have you
know, they they sank like lead in the in the ים סוף.
Yam Suf. באדירים be'adirim and that they were paid back that they
were conquered or paid back in the in the אדירים adirim אלו
המים, elu hamayim, that's the water. שנאמר מקולות מים רבים אדירים משברי
ים shenemar mikolot mayim rabim adirim mishberei yam from the many waters,
the sound of the many waters, אדירים adirim powerful are these you
know the breaking waves of the sea. Okay, so therefore Jews are
paid back from the you know the the gold of the Egyptians,
the treasures of the Egyptians when they were you know wiped out
in the ים סוף. Yam Suf. Okay, so they are paid back
אדיר באדיר. adir be'adir. Now, what seems to be the point here?
Well, let's read one more, but we'll you'll see the theme and
then we can talk about how this might have been his response.
But at least here we'll note that he reads אדירים adirim not
to be אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov but to be ישראל.
Yisrael. יבא ידיד בן ידיד yavo yedid ben yedid let
same same
רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, it's giving a similar string of דרשות. drashot.
יבא רב עזרא, yavo Rav Ezra, what's his name? I don't know
what his name is. רב עזרא. Rav Ezra. Okay. Notice he has
the name of his great-great-grandfather. Yeah, it's עזרא בר בריה דאבטולס Ezra
bar bereih de'Avtulas was him, but אלעזר בן עזריה Elazar ben Azaryah
which is right, exactly. So he really likes his family name and
his ייחוס. yichus. Okay. Exactly. So יבא ידיד בן ידיד yavo yedid
ben yedid so let the beloved one, the son of the beloved
one come, ויבנה ידיד veyivneh yedid and build the beloved place as
we'll see, לידיד leyedid for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for the
beloved one, for God בחלקו של ידיד bechelko shel yedid in the
portion of the beloved one ויתכפרו בו ידידים veyitkapru vo yedidim
and then the beloved people will be atoned for. So who is
this? יבא ידיד זה שלמה המלך yavo yedid ze Shlomo HaMelech that's
Shlomo דכתיב וישלח ביד נתן הנביא ויקרא שמו ידידיה בעבור כי ה׳
אהבו dechitiv vayishlach beyad Natan HaNavi vayikra shemo Yedidyah ba'avur ki Hashem
aheivo Shlomo was called ידידיה Yedidyah ba'avur ki Hashem aheivo anyway for
God anyway.
Anyway,
בן ידיד ben yedid the son of a ידיד yedid זה אברהם
ze Avraham not דוד, David, interesting, this is אברהם Avraham דכתיב מה
לידידי בביתי dechitiv mah liyedidi beveisi what is my beloved one doing
in my house? We'll see that the פסוק pasuk by ירמיה Yirmiyah
which we're going to דרוש darush about אברהם Avraham in a minute,
ויבנה ידיד veyivneh yedid build the beloved thing זה בית המקדש ze
Beis HaMikdash דכתיב מה ידידות משכנותיך dechitiv mah yedidos mishkenosecha
so that's the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it says how beloved is
your dwelling place, לידיד leyedid for the beloved one זה הקדוש ברוך
הוא ze Hakadosh Baruch Hu דכתיב אשירה נא לידידי dechitiv ashirah na
liyedidi I will now sing to my beloved one, בחלקו של ידיד
bechelko shel yedid in the portion of the beloved one זה בנימין
ze Binyamin because the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was in the portion
of בנימין Binyamin שנאמר לבנימין אמר ידיד
ה׳ ישכן לבטח עליו shenemar leBinyamin amar yedid Hashem yishkon lavetach alav
God will dwell for you know in בנימין Binyamin ויתכפרו בו ידידים
veyitkapru vo yedidim
and let the beloved ones be atoned for אלו ישראל elu Yisrael
this is Israel דכתיב נתתי את ידידות נפשי בכף אויביה dechitiv nasati
es yedidus nafshi bechaf oyveha
I have given over the beloved of my soul into the hands
of their enemies. This was ירמיה Yirmiyah prophesying for bad, but anyway
you see that Israel is called ידידות yedidus the beloved. Okay, now
similarly יבא טוב yavo tov let the good come ויקבל טוב veyekabel
tov the good people ויקבל טוב מטוב veyekabel tov mitov
and receive good from the good one לטובים letovim
for good. What is this? יבא טוב yavo tov let the good
come זה משה ze Moshe דכתיב ותרא אותו כי טוב הוא dechitiv
vateira oso ki tov hu Moshe was good, right? So he's טוב
tov ויקבל טוב veyekabel tov and receive the טוב tov זו תורה
zu Torah דכתיב כי לקח טוב נתתי לכם dechitiv ki lekach tov
nasati lachem I've given you this good taking. מטוב mitov
from the good one זה הקדוש ברוך הוא ze Hakadosh Baruch Hu
get the טוב tov
God is good to all. לטובים Le-tovim and receive the תורה Torah
for the good people, אלו ישראל, elu Yisrael, דכתיב הטיבה ה' לטובים.
dechtiv heitivah Hashem le-tovim.
God has done good for the good, for the good people. Okay,
one last דרשה. drasha. יבוא זה ויקבל זאת, Yavo zeh veyekabel zot,
let this one... of all the things this seems the weakest, but
it seems like the emphasis is because other things at least were,
you know, were somehow descriptive adjectives, characteristics, but it seems like the
idea of זה zeh pointing something out is saying this is like
a model, a paradigm, an important thing. So let the זה zeh
come. יבוא זה, Yavo zeh, let me see, ויקבל זאת, veyekabel zot,
and let him get the this, מזה mizeh from the that, לעם
זו le-am zu for this people. יבוא זה, Yavo zeh, וזה זה
משה, vezeh zeh Moshe, דכתיב כי זה משה האיש, dechtiv ki zeh
Moshe ha-ish,
this man Moshe. ויקבל זאת, Veyekabel zot, let him get the this,
זאת תורה, zot Torah, דכתיב וזאת התורה, dechtiv vezot ha-Torah,
this is the Torah. So Moshe is maybe unique or distinct, let
him get the Torah which is unique or distinct. Okay, and
who does he get it from? מזה Mizeh from this, זה הקדוש
ברוך הוא, zeh HaKadosh Baruch Hu, דכתיב זה קלי ואנוהו, dechtiv zeh
Keli ve-anvehu, this is my God. לעם זו Le-am zu for this
nation, אלו ישראל elu Yisrael שנאמר עם זו קנית, shene'emar am zu
kanita, this people that you have, that you have owned or that
you have created. Now how is this relevant other than that oh
look you have these similar things? So I think what he's saying
is all of this talks about affinity, right? You know, טוב tov
gives to טובים, tovim, sometimes in one case with מצרים Mitzrayim it
was a little bit off because they're getting paid back from the
אדירים, adirim, but nevertheless, that means that these things, you know, there's
an affinity to these types of things and therefore it makes sense
that the good gives the good thing to the good people, you
know, the beloved is building the beloved place for the beloved one
for God and so on. When there's an affinity these things happen
together and I think what he's saying is the opposite. He's saying
as as Sifra pointed out, here he's a רב עזרא Reb Ezra
whose grandfather was עזרא בן עזריה, Ezra ben Azarya, whose great-great-great-whatever, not
Ezra's, 20 years was was עזרא הסופר. Ezra HaSofer. It's let Ezra
come for Ezra for Ezra, you know what I'm saying? He's saying
look, my יחוס yichus means something. You know, it's you know and
therefore you know if I have my great-great-grandparents were you know were
tremendous תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and was עזרא הסופר Ezra HaSofer who
brought the תורה Torah to כלל ישראל, Klall Yisrael,
then that means that there's some of that is going to accrue
to my benefit. You know, something will be you know somehow, I
mean I'm not, I think what he's not saying is like I
just want credit like okay you got a great grandparent, but what
I think he's saying is that you know the יחוס yichus actually
has some impact on who I am and these types of, when
these things have some affinity they actually work together. And therefore
yeah, I would, I would like a little respect from the fact
that I have... Now it's interesting, the גרסא girsa before, because when
רב פפא Rav Pappa said if he's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and has יחוס, yichus, so our גרסא girsa says just יא יא,
ya ya, it's good. But the other גרסא girsa has יא ויא,
ya ve-ya, it's good and it's good. So then he's sort of
that is essentially I think what he's sort of saying back. He's
saying I admit maybe if I don't have תורה Torah I don't
want just credit for the fact that I've got, you know, nice
יחוס. yichus. But if I have תורה Torah and I come from
a family, a rabbinic family as it were, a family of תורה,
Torah, then you know that should be sort of seen as doubly
to my credit, that that's sort of maybe that, you know, the
genes or the or the upbringing or whatever it is, there's a
reason why, you know, these things somehow work together. Like you do
find that, you do find rabbinic families of very profound תלמידי חכמים.
talmidei chachamim. I mean my God, think about, you know, רש"י, Rashi,
רב סולובייצ'יק, Rav Soloveitchik, think about, you know, רש"י, Rashi, whose grandsons
were רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and the רשב"ם, Rashbam, and then the
ר"י Ri was the nephew. I mean basically the entire ש"ס Shas
in front of us, you know, everything on the side of the
גמרא Gemara was written by one family.
I'm serious, רש"י Rashi and the תוספות, Tosafot, right? The רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam and the ר"י Ri is תוספות, Tosafot, and רש"י, Rashi,
it's all written by one family. So you do find sometimes a
power in these types of things, you know? So it's sort of
like what the גמרא Gemara says, you know, where it says that
you know God is משלם, meshaleim, you know, when is God משלם
meshaleim the עונש onesh on the next generation and when is he
not, or when does God pay the reward of, you know, you
know, you know, you know
to future generations? So the גמרא Gemara often speaks about when it's
מחזיק מעשי אבותיו בידו, machzik ma'asei avotav beyado, you know, if you're
following in the steps of your parents, whether it's for good or
for bad, you know, but that reinforces, you know, what you you
what you yourself are doing. So that seems to in my mind
seems to sort of be his response back. You know, I do
deserve a little credit.
And there's a little bit, maybe a little bit different perspective, although
it doesn't, one doesn't negate the other. There's a poetry in it,
and the way that it's expressed about יבוא ידיד yavo yedid זה
ידיד, zeh yedid, that
there's just a poetry in life.
Oh I see, in that, oh that's nice.
When, you know, when families carry on this tradition.
Uh-huh, uh-huh. Well that's a nice point. Best of both worlds. That's
a nice point.
Okay. But the reason the whole thing is here...
Yeah, so that is never explained.
Is it because of
רב פרידא Rav Preida was there before? But was רב פרידא Rav
Preida even before this? Yeah, he was the one that was read
before. It would be... Oh, because רב פרידא Rav Preida introduced...
So we're just doing רב פרידא... Rav Preida...
Right, right, it's a great story. And there are some that try
to connect them. I will say we have to stop here, but
the end of this דרשנ'ס darshens the same פסוקים psukim and talks
about the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. So at least it relates in
some way to קדשים Kodshim theme, although we haven't been discussing anything
about חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. So that will be continued tomorrow.